[Music]
Stanford
University all right uh there was a
there was an issue that came up the last
time and I didn't understand the
question there was a question that kept
coming up and I didn't understand what
it was until the very end of the uh
class uh and it was an interesting and a
good question so I want to go over it uh
because it is important it had to do
with spin in a magnetic field emitting a
photon and I maintained that if it emits
a photon remember the um the the way we
set things up we said let's take the
hamiltonian to be Omega over 2 let's say
Sigma
Z that has two igen values plus Omega
over 2 and minus Omega over two so the
two I values let's call it E1 for energy
the lower of the two igen values is
minus Omega / 2 and the upper one uh
is Let's see we could call this e minus
and
e+ is plus Omega over 2 so there are two
energy levels if we drew an energy level
diagram energy we would have two igen
values it would be zero over here but
that would not be one of them and then
we would have one over here Omega over
two and minus Omega over
2 all right now what can happen under
such under we are not we have not
studied this process yet but let's talk
about it for a moment given two states
like this it is possible for an atom or
a spin or or a system with energy levels
like this to emit a photon emit a photon
and go from the upper one to the lower
one if it's in the upper if it's in a
lower State obviously it cannot emit a
photon doesn't have the energy to do it
but if it's in the Upper State it can
emit a
photon and that Photon will have the
energy difference between the upper and
lower state so we'll have an energy of
frequency or energy
Omega sorry not frequency it will be
frequency but more important it will
have energy of Omega there's an har bar
missing I've been setting har bar equal
to zero no h bar equal
one I've been setting H bar equal to
one uh it's really H bar Omega but I'll
continue to set H equal to one because
we're all grown ups and uh we're not
we're not afraid of setting H bar equal
to one
right what it was Zero last
quarter it was Zero last quarter yes it
was Zero last quarter that's
correct right okay so we draw a picture
with a photon a transition and a photon
being emitted
now somebody said what if the spin was
not pointed up or down what if it were
pointed here's the z-axis what if it
were pointed well let's say this way
along the x-
axis and then it emitted a photon would
it not emit a photon of half the energy
namely Omega over two and the answer is
no it would not emit a photon of energy
Omega over two let's talk discuss first
what what happened classically
classically if we had a rotor a spinning
rotor in a magnetic field that had an
energy which was the typical energy
would be the co proportional to the
cosine of the angle between the axis of
the spin here's the axis of the spin
here's the magnetic
field uh the energy of that rotating
object would depend on the orientation
of the spin relative to the magnetic
field
the energy would be minimum down and it
would gradually increase until it were
up all right that's number one number
two classically and Quantum mechanically
classically the actual value uh Quantum
mechanically the expectation value of
the spin precesses around the B axis
with frequency
Omega that also happens
classically it's in the classical
mechanics not notes in the Pome bracket
um
section where we studied exactly that
question it wasn't called spin it was
called angular momentum the spinning top
uh does exactly the same thing and that
spinning top if it really is a little
electromagnet a little
um uh magnetic system rotating it will
radiate in the process of going around
with frequency Omega it will emit
radiation at what
frequency Omega it'll emit fre radiation
at the and how much radiation will it
emit now it's classical it's not
emitting photons it's emitting classical
radiation and it will gradually as it
emits radiation fall over until it gets
down and then no more radiation how much
energy will it emit all
together and the answer depends on the
angle uh that it's started at if it
starts up it will emit all together an
amount of energy that's proportional
essentially
Omega if it's pointing down it will emit
no energy if it's pointing horizontally
it will emit let's say Omega over two so
there'll be a continuous possible value
of emission of radiation at the same
frequency Quantum mechanically
it can only emit a photon with whatever
energy that Photon has and the answer is
a diff it's a it's a related but
different answer if it emits it will
emit a photon
of energy
Omega on the other hand the probability
of whether it emits is not one
necessarily in fact let's suppose that
the initial
state is some
Alpha up plus beta
down if Alpha and beta are equal that
corresponds to being oriented along the
x-axis if Alpha is 1 and beta is zero
that's pointing up if Alpha is zero and
beta is one that's pointing
down an up electron or an up spin will
emit a photon of AEG Omega of frequency
Omega of energy Omega so if there was
just the upstate yes indeed it would
emit Omega if it was the down state it
emits nothing if it starts in the
superposition of States then with
probability Alpha star Alpha it emits
and with probability beta star beta it
doesn't
emit what is the average energy given
that there's a probability Alpha star
Alpha that he Ms with a a photon of
frequency Omega energy Omega and beta
star beta that emits nothing what is the
average energy and the average energy is
the same as the classical
energy the average energy is the same as
the classical energy but each individual
event emits a photon of
either either emits no Photon or emits a
photon of energy Omega okay so this was
a who asked the question question
somebody here asked the question yeah is
that the that yeah okay so that's the
that's the
upshot and it's sort of internal
consistency of quantum mechanics now of
course to really
yeah um if if the uh electron will will
emit a photon when it goes down in
energy presumably it could observe a
photon yes yes that's correct how
precise would would that Photon have to
be to
Omega uh that depends on the lifetime of
the state and which in turn depends on
how strongly coupled the uh depends it
depends on the magnitude of the dipole
moment the stronger the dipole moment
the magnetic dipole moment the faster it
will emit the faster it emits in other
words the shorter the lifetime of the
excited state will be it's the inverse
lifetime which sets the scale of exactly
what you're asking the the uh the
Precision with which you have to be at
exactly
uh uh there's a spread in the energy
levels there's a spread in the energy
levels or an uncertainty in the energy
levels and the uncertainty in the energy
levels is inverse to the um to the
lifetime of the state so right so you're
absolutely right there there is a spread
and uh it's governed by
the energy time uncertainty principle
but we're not there yet okay whether we
get there or not I don't know okay is
this phenomenon of um of photon emission
what's used in to create an apparatus to
detect in what apparatus to create to
create an apparatus that detects spin of
an
electron that's one way that's one way
to do it that's one way to do it I
decided not to think about that as an
apparatus because I didn't like it it
didn't satisfy the rule that um that if
you measure a component of spin you
leave the system with exactly that uh
that and I after thinking about it I
decided that did not qualify as a
genuine uh uh measuring
apparatus yeah so uh we're going to come
we're going to come to measurements and
the meaning of measurements in a little
while but uh would assum it's a half an
hour gone
already um
okay if there are no more questions I
want to move on to the subject of
entanglement I had a few words to say
about the collapse of a wave function
let's let's just talk about for a moment
the idea of collapse of the wave
function we talked about how Quantum
States evolve according to the
Schrodinger equation and that is the way
they evolve but that's the way they
evolve
between events where somebody or
something a detector or an apparatus or
just some other system an external
system interacts with uh with the
original Quantum system so we have a
Quantum system we have other things in
the world including observers and
including
apparatuses and just including other
things
if we take away all the other things
the system might be left in some State
and the system will then evolve
according to the Stringer equation and
then we may be bring back the other
things the other things might be an
apparatus where did our apparatus go our
apparatus is hiding but uh but um it
could be our
apparatus or something else but let's
say it's an apparatus and the apparatus
measures some specific thing then what
happens during the course of the
interaction with the apparatus
is a measurement takes place and the
system is left in an igen
State corresponding to the particular
outcome so for example we might start
let's suppose we want to measure
L and our system after a while might be
in a state some summation over I a bunch
of complex numbers Alpha subi times igen
vectors of L igen vectors of L with uh
with igen value Lambda subi okay what's
the probability for the outcome of the
experiment the system got here by
evolving using the Schrodinger equation
we started it out we evolved it with a
schinger equation here's what we got at
the end of the day and now we make a
measurement of L and we get some
specific value of Lambda random we don't
know what it's going to be but it's
going to be something let's say it's
Lambda 7 we measure Lambda 7 thereafter
or right after that the system is in
state Lambda
7 the course of the operation of
measurement is not governed by the
Schrodinger equation for the system it's
governed by the nature of the measuring
process and it simply tells you that
you'll come out with one of the igen
values as the measured value and the
state Vector will be just one of these
which one random random depending on the
measurement now that's funny because you
might think look F well first of all
let's give it a terminology the
terminology is the wave function has
collapsed around one point it has
collapsed around one single igen value
you can't predict which one
but all of the structure here with all
the other ones becomes irrelevant and
only one
state pops into existence so to speak
all right now what's wrong with this
what's wrong with
this um well Absol there's absolutely
nothing wrong with it it's a correct
description of the measurement process
but what uh is very unsatisfying about
it is after all apparatuses are just
Quantum
systems uh why do we have two rules for
the way systems
evolve one the Schrodinger equation and
one this arbitrary collapse of the wave
function and the answer is
that
we if we want to think Quantum
mechanically about the whole system of
system plus apparatus that's fine we can
do it and I hope we'll get to it
tonight and then it's pure schinger
equation but we cannot separ separate
the system into just system and
apparatus we have to think about the
whole Quantum system as being system
plus apparatus that raises the question
immediately right now how do you combine
systems together if you have more than
one system it could
be an electron Spin and the
apparatus we have two systems now
imagine we had a good quantum theory of
the apparatus the apparatus is a
physical system Quantum quantum Theory
governs it how do we describe the
combined system where we take two
components one spin one apparatus put
them together how do we make it into a
single Quantum system and then how with
that single Quantum system do we
describe this process of
measurement that is a very it has
confused generations of
physicists partly because bore was very
uh stubborn about this and didn't really
quite have it right
and
um he was a nice man he was a very nice
man I'm very glad I never met
him no he was a nice man but the thing
is he was also a very stubborn man and
uh in this particular thing you he was
most mostly right but uh here and there
he was wrong and there was a apparently
it was very tough to be around him when
he
was people tried to explain to him over
and over again you have to think of the
combined system and you have to think of
the combined Quantum system if you want
to understand the quantum mechanics of
measurement and he said no he didn't
believe that anyway um combined system
we have two systems now let's just not
worry about what they are they are two
systems we'll get more specific in a
moment but let's give them
names let's call one of the systems a
and a does not stand it could stand the
apparatus but it doesn't have to it's
just a system a and we'll call the space
of states of system a s Suba s Suba
could stand for system a but now I have
it to mean the space of quantum states
of the system a and we have another
system I'm going to call
I uh it's another system I with its own
space of States I this the the system a
has states which are
labeled by a basis of
States you choose a basis of states in
the system a and you label them a a can
go from one to whatever the number of
states of system a is whatever the
dimensionality of the space of States a
is and system I has States
I any
any state of system a if you didn't have
I would be a superposition of these
basis States any state of system I would
be a superposition of these basis States
okay how do we put the systems together
and make a single Quantum system well
I'm going to tell you what the rule is
I'll give you a cookbook rule but it's
it's it's pretty uh compelling and it is
the way real things work okay you build
a space of states of the system a i
which means a and I together both of
them that space of
states is
called mathematically it is what is
called the tensor product I'll tell you
what it means in detail but it's the
tensor product of the two space of
States sa this is the symbol for tensor
product SI
now what does a tensor product mean well
it means something very simple it means
you construct a new space new
mathematical space whose vectors are
labeled by a value of a and a value of I
in other words you pair off the basis
vectors in all possible pairings one
from a one from
I and you construct a
basis which is labeled
AI if this let's suppose the
dimensionality of this space is D
Suba and the dimensionality of this
space is d sub
I or d sub I guess it's capital A I want
here d sub capital
A and D sub capital
I in other words the number of
orthogonal states of each one of these
separate
then what's the um what's the
dimensionality of the tensor
product da time di I you get to pick one
from a and one from I like in the
Chinese restaurant one from a and one
from I okay and how many are there all
together da * di that's why it's called
a product because the dimensionality is
uh is a
product so this is Da time
di in Di
diality these are the basis States for
the tensor product okay they're labeled
with two indices now you think of them
as an orthonormal basis orthonormal in
the following sense if you take two such
vectors Ai and let's say
BJ where b is another one of the basis
vectors of A and J is another one of
the of these what's the inner product
between these let's take these to be um
Ortho let's take these to be uh
normalized vectors what is the inner
product between them and the rule for a
tensor product is the inner product
between this and this of course we have
to make a bra Vector out of it in order
to um in order to take its inner product
but if we made a bra Vector out of this
and took its inner product with this one
the rule is that the inner product is
zero unless a is equal to B and I is
equal to J in other words unless they
match okay if they don't
match these might be observably
different for example if this B was the
same as this a but I was not the same as
J then one half of the system here would
be would uh would be there would be
observable differences associated with
observable dist differences in the
subsystem
I so in order for them to have an
overlap B must equal a and j must equal
I and then they're observably uh the
same Vector excuse me are these
arbitrary vectors A and these are basis
vectors these are part of an ormal basis
yes you could pick any orthonormal basis
for this one and any orthonormal basis
for this
one yeah yeah but you could pick any any
orthonormal basis from this one and any
orthonormal basis from this one
and put them together this way and
you'll get the same result doesn't
matter which basis you pick but uh but
let's pick a basis to be concrete let's
pick a
basis if a and I are not the same as
both B and J the inner product is zero I
can write an equation for
that
BJ
AI is equal to Delta chronica
Delta AB chronica Delta i
j if I is not equal to
J or a is not equal to B this is zero
it's only non zero if I is equal to J
and a is equal to
B so these vectors formally by
construction by construction which means
you're simply assigning values to things
now but in a way that uh that uh is
useful the these vectors form by
definition or by construction an
orthonormal basis for the combined
system and this this makes
sense um as you've defined it it's
dependent upon the basis but I still it
does but actually as I defined it let's
put it this way the words depended on
the basis the construction in the end
doesn't the construction in the end
doesn't and that's not hard to show this
is however keep in mind that these basis
vectors are not all of the vectors in
the tensor product you can then take any
linear combination of these basis
vectors and they're also
a vector in the tensor product so the
general Vector in the tensor product is
of the form sum over I and
a alpha let's call it some i
a i
a a general linear combination with
coefficients that depend on what's
inside here times the vector times the
basis vectors now the answer is if you
were to have chosen another ve another
basis another set of bases you would
have gotten except exactly the same
vectors except they would have been
written differently they would have just
been written in a different basis of the
combined system changing basis for the
individual systems corresponds to a
basis change for the combin system okay
so that's that's good and we now have
the idea of a tensor product and I'm
going to give you a concrete example now
the concrete example is the next most
complicated Quantum
system namely two
spins well it's debatable whether it's
the next most complicated or the next
the next most complicated and the reason
I say that is because two spins have
four basis vectors you could imagine a
system with only three basis vectors and
such systems exist but
um but since we're trying to learn how
to combine systems let's take two
systems and combine them each of them
being a spin so what do we have we have
an electron nailed down at this position
over here and it has a spin which we're
going to call Sigma and it has three
components Sigma X Y and Z so Sigma x y
and
z
okay and we have another one over here
we need a name for it now I toyed for a
while with calling this one Sigma 1 and
this one Sigma 2 but there were too many
there were too many indices then I had
Sigma 1X Sigma 1 y bad so I decided to
give this one another name and the Greek
letter that comes after sigma is Tao I
don't know if it's the next letter it's
the one in the English alphabet that's T
yeah so the next one I think in the
Greek alphabet is Tao
and I simply call this one
TOA how many components does to have
well TOA is also a spin so it also has
three components X Y and
Z supposing I choose for the basis
vectors for each of these the up and
down bases vectors in other words the
states in which Sigma Z is up or down
and the states in which to Z are up and
down then our basis vectors for Sigma
are
up and
down our basis vectors for too are
exactly the
same
up and down and maybe in order to
indicate that these are vectors
for the system to and these are vectors
for the system Sigma let's use a
slightly different kind of bracket
notation here let's use a cur let's use
a curly uh
bracket I'm going to give that up very
shortly I just want to I just want to
point out to you that these are
different in these and
down so good what is the basis vectors
for the combined system if we put the
systems together what are the basis
vectors for the combined system there
are four of them 2 * 2 is four and what
are they they are states in which both
spins are
up it's one of them one Spin and I'll
always take the first entry here to
correspond to Sigma and the second entry
to correspond to towel up
down down
up and down
down that's that's the four basis
vectors each basis Vector carrying two
labels now a a sigma label and a towel
label that's the idea and it's a know
it's a very reasonable
idea yes suppose these two component
systems interact doesn't that change
things Som no the basis vectors stay the
same but the linear combination of basis
vectors that they're describing the
system will change yeah so any state in
the space can be written as an alpha up
up time up
up plus an alpha up down up
down plus an alpha down
up down up plus an alpha down
down down
down that's the most General thing we
can write
right it's called sigh the answer to
your question is if you started out with
a particular linear
combination let's say for example just
Alpha up up up up both spins up and you
let them interact then in general what
will happen is these coefficients will
change in fact it could even happen that
after a Time Alpha up up might go to
Alpha down
down in other words two spins up might
interact in such a way is to just uh
wind up down that would not be a change
in what the basis vectors are it would
be a change in what the alphas are okay
so
uh all right now there are several
questions we can ask incidentally one of
the one of the um criteria for doing
this correctly is that if we take the
combined system but then we only do
experiments on one of the halves of
it the other one doing whatever it's
doing and they're well separated from
each other let's suppose they're well
separated from each other and we do
experiments on only one of them the
answers that we get should be the same
answers that we got when we didn't even
think of it as a combined system if we
have a theory of Sigma which we've
talked about now for five weeks I think
and we know all about it we know how to
do experiments on it and now we think of
it as half a system composed of Sigma
and too but Sigma and TOA are far from
each other let's say they're not
interacting with each other
substantially and we do exactly the same
experiments that we've been talking
about up till now we should get the same
answers so we should put these things
together in a way which makes sure that
the
earlier um issues the earlier
description of either subsystem is still
correct now I'm not I'm not going to
bother proving that I think you'll get
the idea and you'll see how it works and
the way we are putting things together
does guarantee
that okay now we can go in two
directions from here we can talk about
the space of states or we can talk about
the observables and we're going to do
both we're going to do both but I'll
take a vote how many people want to talk
about the space of
States how many want to talk about the
observables we'll talk about the space
of States first you knew I was going to
do that come on you know I going to do
that all right uh
yeah one
question are we allowed to pick left and
right for the second what oh yeah yeah
yeah sure there are there are yeah
supposing we wanted um supposing we
wanted a state which was left for Sigma
and up for
to all right so this would be an ex this
would be a state which would be prepared
we have two apparatuses now I'm always
uncomfortable with the word apparatuses
I always think it should be apparati but
I don't think that's right we have two
apparatuses one that we apply to Sigma
the other that we appli to toao and we
now take our apparatus one apparatus the
sigma apparatus we point it in the let's
say the XY AIS the not the XY along the
x- axis and the other one and we point
along the
z-axis and we wind up discovering that
Sigma was along the x-axis with plus1
and to was along the z-axis also with +
one so that means that
Sigma was
up but too was
right how do we make a state which
is so the answer is this you I'll tell
you what you do but we'll we'll
eventually have a mathematics to
this Sigma is definitely
up but to is a linear superposition of
up with
down easy you just take up up plus up
down square > of two 1 overun of
two you can think of this another way
you can say the think of it as a product
a product of
up
for Sigma and
right for
too now what is right right is up plus
down right right right is up plus down
so this can also be written as up times
and I'm going to put a big square
bracket around it
up squiggly bracket plus
down but if I want to normalize it I
should put a square root of two
downstairs so we just think of it as a
product
of Sigma up and to in the along the
right
direction but that's the same thing here
uh we have 1/ < TK of two up up that's
this one
one and 1/ < TK of two up down that's
this
one okay I'm not sure if this answered
your question or not I think it probably
partly did yeah okay right and you know
okay this kind of state is called a
product State it's a product state in
which you know exactly what's going on
with Sigma namely it's in the up
direction and you know exactly what's
going along on with to it's in the right
direction there's a product State and
and it's simply two separate things
which were prepared
independently and here it
is um a product state is by definition a
product let's write the most General
product
State the most General this is not a
this this is not the most General
product State the most General product
State can be written as
follows Alpha up
up plus Alpha down
down that's for Sigma and then for
too let's call it beta let's call the
coefficients for for to let's call them
beta beta
up up
squiggly plus beta
down
down what does this mean this means that
Sigma was prepared in this particular
linear combination here it might have
been by holding your detector in some
funny angle and this one is the response
to holding the tow detector at some
other
angle had you had only one of these not
the other you would just have written
this down had the other one you would
have written this down together you
write down the product that's the rule
okay that's the rule and of course you
know ultimately these rules are the
rules because they agree with experiment
but uh but it's a pretty plausible rule
this is a product we could also write it
Alpha up beta uptimes up
up plus Alpha up beta down up down do I
need to write the rest of
it well I
will plus Alpha down beta
up down
up plus Alpha down beta down
down
down all right now of course this is of
the form of a general Vector but there's
something special about the coefficients
here the co the the coefficients
factorize into and and uh uh therefore
this is in a certain sense special to
some extent let's see if we can quantify
how
special yeah what kind of vector product
is that that's that's a product this is
an element of a tensor product and it's
the tensor product of this Vector with
that
Vector it's a vector drawn in the
composite
system as a tensor product of a vector
describing one system and a vector
describing the other
system so strictly speaking the tens of
product is usually used for the whole
space but then you would say this is a
product state within the tens of product
space and I I'll just call a tensor
product state or product
State it's not General and to see how
non-general it is we can count
parameters
given a general system a general State
Vector how many parameters how many
independent parameters does it take to
describe
it and the answer is four complex
numbers Alpha up up Alpha up down Alpha
down up Alpha down down I am not
assuming that it has this special form
just general four numbers four complex
numbers is eight real numbers but I but
that's a little too much because we
should assume that the state is
normalized so that's one constraint and
we also know the overall phase is not
important so when you count parameters
you always subtract two one for the
normalization and one for the phase 8 -
2 is 6
six real
parameters describing a general state of
two
spins how many
here well the state describing the sigma
particle that has two real
parameters four real parameters for
Alpha up and Alpha down but then we
subtract two same thing
here this is a normalized state and its
overall phase doesn't matter this is a
normalized state its overall phase
doesn't matter altogether for real
parameters it's the same four real
parameters that you might have guessed
if you just said I have two spins each
spin had two parameters necessary to
write down its state two real parameters
the real parameters could have been the
polarization directions of the
spin the axis along which the spin is
oriented
or so there are four four parameters
here but six parameters
here that simply proves that not all
states are product States in fact Most
states are not product States we're
going to talk about some non-product
states soon
enough but this is the notion of a
product
State and in the product State we can
really think of separate states for each
of the particles or each of the
subsystems but for a more General State
you can't really divide it into a state
for one subsystem and a state for the
other subsystem they're entangled
they're entangled in a more elaborate
and more more
uh
um I don't know what the word is
entangled they're entangled in a more
entangled
way we're going to discuss that
entanglement that's a very important
concept of
course okay so that's two spins how many
parameters 6 versus 4 they're entangled
right we've talked about product States
and that's what we know about the space
of states of this system it takes six
parameters to describe it but only four
parameters if it's a product State
product states are the ones for which
you can separately say there's a state
for one system and a state for the other
system end of
story okay now let's talk about
observables now we come to
observables what are the observables for
this composite
system well they must be the same
observables as for the separate systems
by themselves in other words Sigma X Y
and Z and to X Y and
Z they are the things you could measure
with two
apparatuses of the same kind as we used
in our experiment
on one spin we now have two of them and
so we have Sigma X Sigma Y and sigma Z
and tox toy and to Z let's see if we can
figure out how these operators ought to
operate on the states of the combined
system all right now you can sort of
guess I'll spell it out but here's the
rule let's take Sigma
X and let's apply it to a state of the
sigma system obviously it belongs with
the sigma
system if it applies to up it gives down
if it applies to down it gives
up you can check that that's the fact
that Sigma X is equal to 0 1 1 0 this
off diagonal character means it takes up
to down and down to up right this is
what Sigma X does ordinarily if we only
had one subsystem here's what it does on
the combined system Sigma X on any
Vector which begins with up and has
anything let's see uh which one was a
and which one was
I second one was
i t went with I or to went with to was I
okay so Sigma
X when it acts on up
I all it sees is the up all it sees is
the first thing here and it's completely
passive with respect to the second index
in other words it doesn't even notice a
second index it leaves it the same it
doesn't change it but it does whatever
it should
do on the first
entry likewise Sigma X
on down
I equals up
I you just take what it did for the
Single part for the single uh spin space
and you just think of the other index as
a kind of spectator that just goes along
for the
ride doesn't do anything on the other
hand oh let's do one more Sigma let's
one more Sigma Sigma
Z on up
I well what does Sigma Z do when it gets
when it acts on
up Sigma Z is 1 minus
one 0
0 it just gives back up with value one
so that's
just up
I and what about Sigma Z on down
I well what happens when Sigma Z hits
down minus down so this gives minus down
I how about Sigma Y what does Sigma well
Sigma y does something very much the
same as Sigma X except it throws an I
not this I but the numerical complex
number I throws it around because what
is it Sigma X this is Sigma
Z Sigma X was 1 - one and sigma y
was equal to minus i i0 0 Sigma y also
flips up to down and down to up but it
throws in grous eye here and there okay
so that's that's what Sigma does now how
about too well towel
does exactly the same thing
except
that the first entry becomes The
Spectator and only the second entry gets
uh gets acted on so let's uh let's do
this
one how let's say x on
a
up a could be anything now a can be up
or down doesn't matter tox on a up is
equal to
a time down and to
x on
a
down is equal to
up all right let's do to
Z on
a
up equals a
up and t
z on a Down
is equal to minus a
down and you could figure out the action
of um of the Y components of the
spin uh
straightforward with this
definition it's quite clear that if
you're talking about an observable
associated with
Sigma that the tow degrees of freedom
are completely passive nothing happens
to them the IG
vectors of the components of
Sigma are simply product states of the
igen vectors of Sigma times any Vector
for
too in other words for example the igen
vector the igen vectors the IG Vector
yeah vectors
of let's take Sigma y
ordinarily the igen vectors of Sigma y
are 1
I
or 1 minus I I can't remember which one
has igen Value Plus One or minus one but
one of the others right uh that means
that means the linear combination up
plus I down that's an igen Vector of
Sigma y if you want the igen vector of
Sigma y
when we're talking about the composite
system it's exactly the same except you
put an Al an i in here I guess an i in
here and an i in here same
I same I so for example it could be up
up plus I down up or up down plus I down
down the I is a spectator it just goes
along for the ride anything which was an
igen Vector for the single
system remains an igen Vector for for
the single system except you have to add
in the index for the other particle for
the other uh for the other
subsystem and that's all there is to it
with these definitions as I said it's
pretty clear that the separate
subsystems uh behave uh independently
quite
independently as long as you don't let
them interact and uh and feel each other
or do something interesting with each
other as long as they are kept separated
okay
um other questions question um those
equation Sig X acting on
U Down Sig
X yeah shouldn't shouldn't those since
you have Sig X acting on up Vector
should result in a super position of
Stace no no Sigma
X expanded up in terms of the I states
of of Sigma X
right
well let's just do it by
matrices Sigma X is 1 1 0
0 up is one
Zer okay up is one Z what happens this
times this is
zero this times this is
one so up has gone to
down okay likewise if we put a zero here
and a one
here this would become a one
zero so it just takes one zero and flips
it to a
01 and uh back and forth like that in
general of course you would be right but
for for this particular uh case uh it
just gives you back I I see how the ones
and zeros work out but I'm trying to map
that into the physical situation where
you're you're making measurement of the
X Direction State that's this
way this doesn't say this doesn't
say uh let's
see this doesn't say one Zer and Z1 are
igen vectors of Sigma X far from it it's
about as far from an IG Vector as you
can can get when you act with Sigma X on
this one you get a completely orthogonal
state so this is not the rule that says
this is not the equation that says that
01 or one Zer are igen
vectors uh an igen Vector is a vector
which is kept in the same direction by
action of the operator this is as far as
you can get from that the operator acts
and gives you something
orthogonal and that's okay all right
you'll have to you'll have to work that
out is a linear uh superposition of left
and right it is indeed it
is right
right right that's
correct that that sort of connects to my
question before class which is so is
there any physical meaning to applying
an operator to a non-an vector well what
is that operation equate
to most of the times that's just an
auxiliary operation in some calculation
or other
um
well it doesn't have
any particular special physical
meaning but in this particular case what
it tells you is 01 and one Z are about
as far from igen vectors as you can get
and what it tells you is that um if you
measure Sigma X in an igen state of
Sigma Z it's as random as it can
be okay it's as random as it can
be all right we're going along
good yeah so in this product notation
that you have what happens if I have
Sigma X tox operating
on in the product first equation that
you have tox some Au gives you ad what
happens yes what happens if I had Sigma
X and tox operating on
a mean Sigma x times tox okay we could
work that
out let's do it it's it's a little bit
late it's five minutes later in the
notes but uh let's do it right now since
we're at
it
let's take Sigma
X
tox and tell me what Vector you would
like to apply it
to how
about how about up up let's do up
up what does tox do let's see
I keep forgetting no this one the the
one on the left is Sigma right the this
one's Sigma and this one's to right okay
all right so we start with
too and we hit
this what does tox do it operates on
this one and leaves this one
alone so this gives us do I have it
wrong yeah it operates on this one and
leaves this one alone right okay so it
gives Sigma X I have not act acted with
that yet times now to X flips this one
so it's up
down okay now what does Sigma X
do it flips this
one so it just gives down
down kind of boring but that's what it
does let's do it the opposite
order let's take PX * Sigma X on up
up what does it do it does exactly the
same thing Sigma X hits one of these and
flips them and then tox comes and hits
the other one and flips it so when tox *
Sigma X acts it gives exactly the same
thing as Sigma x *
tox commutator of Sigma x with to x
equals
zero no difference between the order of
operations let's try it for Sigma x * to
Z okay let's do it for Sigma X time t z
and see what we get oh I have not proved
this because I only exhibited for one
particular
state in order to argue that Sigma X x *
tox equal tox * Sigma X
whoops you would have to show that they
give the same thing when acting on any
basis Vector it's enough to show that
they give the same thing on basis
vectors all right but that's pretty
easy not hard to do you can do it on any
basis vector and you'll find out that
the order of operations doesn't matter
in fact the same is
true if you take Sigma x times let's say
t z let's do it again shall I take a
different Vector let's take some other
Vector instead of up down let's take
um down up and see what it does and then
we'll do it in the opposite order all
right what does to Z do when it hits
this Vector
here it only acts on the second entry
and it's a z component so it just gives
plus one on an R
right so this just gives Sigma x
times
down
up to Z on up gives
up so that just goes right through then
what does Sigma X do when it hits down
up this gets to be a little bit go
gobbly g at this point my tongue starts
uh um rebelling
what does Sigma X do when it hits to
when it hits this
guy it just flips down to up it
gives up up
right let's do it in the opposite order
to Z Sigma X on down up all right first
Sigma X that flips down to up so it
gives us to
Z times up
up and then to Z
just gives one when it hits the RP so it
gives the same thing again and you can
sort of see why if if they're acting on
the on separate indices here it doesn't
matter which way you order them this is
very general it doesn't matter which
state you take it doesn't matter which
component you take any component of T
Sigma commutes with any component of to
you can check that just by knowing how
they
act all right so we can say Sigma
anything I'm not sure what to call the
index here
Sigma I don't want to call it I we've
already used I for something but
uh
Sigma n Sigma to M for any n and M they
commute the meaning of that is that if
you have two separate
subsystems which are combined in this
way
the observables for one and the
observables for the other can be
simultaneously
measured in particular if you took the
systems and far apart from each other
and you treat them as a single Quantum
system you would expect that measuring
one of them doesn't interfere with any
measurement of the other
one and that's what this says that
measuring a sigma does not preclude
measuring a tow and and vice versa for
any components of them so in that sense
they behave like independent systems you
can make any measurement on Sigma and
any measurement on to
yeah so what we got so far as we got
these observables on each independent
part of the you know on each piece of
the system then we can think about an
observable as one part is happening in
this system it's as happy as it was
before you added the other
subsystem yes
yes that's a good question are there
observables which are somehow more
intimately connected with having both of
them the answer is yes for example Sigma
times
too Sigma time too Sigma X time to X or
Sigma x * t y that sort of thing um are
observables that somehow know more
intimately about the combination of both
of
them and they know in particular about
entanglement you started with
independent you just said spin sign
spin now how are you how are you linking
them so that they depend on each other
we Haven yet we haven't yet what we've
done up till now is do all the
ingredients which tell you that as long
as you do
separate experiments separate operations
on the two
subsystems that they will behave exactly
as they would have had the other system
not been there but now you can ask what
about are there more are there more in
particular in particular if the system
is the combined system if it's in a
product state if it's in a product state
so that each component has its own State
Vector then the quantum mechanics of
each one of them is separate from the
other they don't interfere with each
other they don't know about each other
in in any way that's what this
prescription
insures no no they're not entangled yet
not if they're product States now what
we found out is a that the products that
the product states are a four parameter
set we found out also that the full
space of States has six parameters so
there are apparently states which are
not product States those are the states
which have to varying degrees a degree
of
entanglement I'm going to write down now
the most entangled state and we're going
to examine it a little
bit and see in what way it's
odd up
down there are many highly entangled
States maximally entangled States I'm
writing one one particular one minus and
I'm putting the minus
here uh just because I happen to know
that it's a a particular has a
particular property which is not so
important at this stage but let's uh
let's put the minus there minus down
up one over < TK of two of course 1 over
> two times the whole
thing now this state is
interesting it has the
property
that if you me well it has a correlation
if you know that to is down then Sigma
must be up on the other hand if you know
that to is up then Sigma must be down
now what does that mean mathematically
we're going to find out exactly what
that means mathematically this is not a
product State there is no way that this
can be written as a product of one state
it's a sum or or difference in this case
of two product States but it is not a
product State how can we tell how can we
tell tell
so let's
consider the expectation value in a
state of the components of
Sigma let's go back to the one subsystem
to the one system quantum mechanics one
Spin and let's ask what do we know about
that in particular I'm interested in
expectation
values
of in any state take a state and take
the expectation value of all three
components this is the average
value I'm not multiplying or anything
I'm just considering them
individually can they all be
zero
can they all simultaneously be zero for
uh for an ordinary state of uh you know
for the ordinary two parameter family of
states of a single
system should we take a vote or should I
just tell
you the answer is no they cannot all be
zero and here's the
reason um
well the reason is given any state there
is always a Direction in space in
three-dimensional
space a direction for which Sigma in
that direction the component of Sigma in
that direction is definite and equal to
plus one given any s this is what I told
you in the very beginning of the lecture
or maybe even before the lecture given
any
state there is some linear combination
of sigmas which is definitely equal to +
one in that case if I find that
particular combination of
sigmas Sigma NX you know do Sigma into n
that particular linear combination its
expectation value can't be zero because
it's definitely up along those that
direction so the answer is given any
state there is always some direction
let's call it sigma. n that depends on S
it depends on s sigma.
n for which this is not only not zero
but it's equal to plus one the a the
average of sigma. in is of course if
sigma. in is definite if it's known and
there's no ambiguity about it then the
average is just equal to the value that
uh that it's known to be so there's
always
some
in all right for any s there exist
exists an
in such
that this is
true therefore it cannot be true that
all of these can simultaneously be
zero for a state of a single
spin you can't measure them all
simultaneously but if I give you a state
I tell you the state then I can then you
can tell me
what direction of space should you
Orient your detector so that the answer
comes out plus
one okay for example I mean I could just
give you up okay so what direction if I
gave you up what direction should uh
should you Orient your
detector along the z-axis what if I gave
you up plus down with sare < TK of
two what direction should you Orient
your uh detector to make sure that you
get plus one
along the x- axis
right what if I gave you up plus I
down I don't know some some either plus
y or minus y okay I forget which one
given any combination there are enough
directions that you can find the
direction for which Sigma in that
direction is definitely + one and
therefore it cannot be the all of these
expectation values are all zero why
because you know that sigma. n is equal
to + one and that's of course just a
linear combination of
these okay so there so as I said it's
impossible if we have just a state of
one spin isolated by itself it's been
prepared
somehow uh however it's prepared there
exists a direction in which the spin is
definite and not equal to
zero okay
um what about the
state what about the state by
now let's take Sigma and ask whether any
of the
components of
Sigma have a nonzero expectation value
in this state what I'm going to show
I'll tell you the answer right now we're
going to show that all three components
of
Sigma have zero expectation value in
this
state that means the state cannot
possibly be a product State a product
state is one in which each component
behaves as if it were just a state of
the subsystem by
itself this state is going to behave in
a way that no simple product State could
possibly behave we're going to find and
so let's do it let's do it um okay let's
put but the square root of two here is
not important that's that's not the
important thing we have up
down minus down
up we're going to take the expectation
value so that means we have to make a
sandwich the sandwich will have up
down minus down up and in the middle
here we're going to put a sigma we could
do the same with too we get the same
answer so let's put Sigma Z first let's
put Sigma Z here and see what we
get first we act with Sigma Z and what
does Sigma Z give when it when it hits
up
down it just gives up down right all
right all right so this just gives up
down but what does it what does it give
when it hits this guy over here minus
down up but there's already a minus down
up so there's a
plus there's already a minus the minus
gets
killed that's over here and that's the
inner product let's put some bracket
around it that's the inner product with
up
down minus down
up okay let's calculate it what's down
up with up down
zero what's down up with down
up one so we get a one what's down up
with up down
oh oh I got something wrong here what
did I do
here this should be up down right yeah
up down Okay so let's go back up down
with up down is
one up down with down up is
zero what about down up with up down
zero what about down up with down
down one but there's a minus sign here
so this is orthogonal to this the inner
product is zero and it says that the
expectation value of Sigma Z is equal to
zero Sigma Z in this state not any state
but in this state is zero let's try
Sigma
X let's try Sigma X next and see what we
get so we have Sigma X
here all right let's build our sandwich
again we have a minus sign
here and what happens when Sigma x
equals up down it hits up
down it flips up to down Sigma X is the
flipper and it flips the first entry
here so it flips the first entry to
down and flips this entry to
up we taking the inner
product with this Vector over here so
let's see are is there anything in
common over here with something in
common here no so there's no way to get
an inner product down up with down down
a zero etc etc again this is
zero so Sigma X is equal to
zero expectation
value okay what about Sigma y let's put
Sigma y
there Sigma Y is also a flip-flop
operator it flips up to down and down to
up but with an I I don't remember which
where the ey goes it either goes
here uh here something something like
that but whatever it does it flips this
up to down so we get a down down and it
flips this down to up so we get an up up
again no inner product is zero so there
we are all three components have zero
expectation value
but that's funny because we
proved well we didn't prove but I told
you told you that if I take any any
state of a single
spin it is never the case that all three
sigmas have zero expectation value
what's the lesson the lesson is that
there are states of the composite system
that can in no way ever be thought of as
separate seate States for the two
subsystems that's what entanglement
is
uh that's an example of
entanglement
yeah so one thing you didn't show here
but maybe it's obvious is that if you do
have a product State then it will
satisfy the same property where one of
them will be yes that's correct that's
correct
well if you show it for the single spin
by
itself then remember the other index
just goes along for the ride so however
you derived it for one spin by itself
you'll do exactly the same derivation
except put a put a sort of spectator
index uh to ride along with it so yeah
it's obvious that if it's
true for one subsystem by itself that it
will be true for the composite what's
not obvious is that it's true for one
subsystem okay so yeah so that's an
exercise that's an exercise to show uh
to show that all three components of
a of the spin cannot of the um
expectation values cannot be zero and
that there's always a direction in which
it's
maximum question um so how do you put a
system in this strange State yeah it's a
very natural state to have I'll I'll
tell you
um if you have to spin and the two spins
are interacting with each
other they will have a um in particular
if they're little magnetic moments then
they will have an interaction with each
other which will prefer to make them
anti-align now this is anti-aligned up
down this is anti-aligned down up and in
fact this combination here has the
lowest energy this combination has the
lowest energy
it has less energy than up down plus
down up so if you bring these two spins
together and you wait a
while they'll radiate a photon
eventually and come to the
state so it's actually not at all hard
to get this kind of state it's rather
easy to get this kind of state and uh
we'll we'll discuss that when we talk
about
interactions but it's a typical
situation that this is what a result if
if you take two spins put them together
and let them come to equilibrium by
radiating a photon
yeah a long
time first of all how close you bring
them together second of all how big the
um the magnetic dipoles of the spin
arm
uh and that has to do with the strength
of coupling to the electromagnetic
field so you know ordinary laboratory
situation uh in an atom the electrons
are close enough together that they will
radiate a photon in not too long a time
to uh to achieve this U so-called
singlet State this is called a singlet
State
singlet I'm not going to tell you why
right
now
uh there are four basis vectors Al
together the reason that this one is
called a singlet is because there are
three others which are the triplet
okay yeah well not not at the moment but
eventually I will tell you the answer
though uh if you think of these as
little angular momenta and you put them
in up down minus down up the total
angular momentum is zero if you put them
down up plus down up the total angular
momentum is one and energy is often
proportional to angular momentum so uh
uh but yeah we can come to that
eventually we'll come to that it's it's
a fair question but uh let's not try to
answer it right this
minute yeah uh if if you take a general
state of of two systems um like we had
uh is it possible to change the basis
such that one basis creates a Subspace
of product SP product States and the
other is purely intended States you're
asking whether the notion of
entanglement is an invariant notion the
answer is yes the answer is yes there's
a very definite quantity that you can
calculate called the entanglement
entropy which measures the strength of
entanglement which is not dependent on
any particular basis now I might tell
you right
now this state okay this state does have
a special feature that up down plus down
up wouldn't have supposing you took the
state and this is good homework
assignment up and down individually for
both Sigma and to can be Rewritten in
terms of left and right for
example uh up is left plus right uh down
is left minus right or whatever it is
square roots of two are there but uh you
know what I mean okay supposing I write
this state I plug in every place I see
down left minus right and every place I
see up left plus right what do I get out
of this the answer is very simple I get
Left Right minus right
left supposing I rewrite it in terms of
in and out what do I
get in
out minus out
in so the structure that the state has
the nature of it is actually the same in
every basis in every basis it looks the
same and that would not be true for up
down plus down up that down up and up
they would they would uh they would
um
uh okay they would get mixed up with
other states there are three other
states this is one there are three
others the three others are well
obviously there were three others and
they mix up with each other when you
change the
basis but this is not obvious this is
not obvious at all all right let's do
one last thing I'm not sure whether
it'll be the last thing or not I think
it's probably the last thing for tonight
um let's ask now about one of these
observables which is not an observable
that can be identified with either
subsystem but which is somehow got to do
with
both and let's look at its expectation
value a very simple
example let's
take
let's take the expectation value of the
product of Sigma Z * to Z we'll do that
one we'll do Sigma x *
tox and maybe we'll do Sigma x x t y or
or Sigma we'll do we'll try some
examples let's take the expectation
value of this now to do this we again
make a
sandwich and
uh all right so let's do it
up down whoops
sorry now I should put the square root
of two in the reason I should put the
square root of two in now is because I'm
not going to get zero so if I really
want to get the numerical number I want
to put that square root of two in and
here we have up down
minus down
up also overare < TK of two so in fact I
can take the square root of twos and put
them all into a factor of 1/2 here this
is the expectation value in the singlet
State we take the singlet State and we
take Sigma Z * to Z let's see what we
get all right first of all when Sigma Z
when to Z acts what does it do do you
remember I don't oh yes to Z doesn't
flip it just gives you a sign which is
Plus for this one and minus for this
one so we can remove the to
Z just by putting a minus sign here
right did I do that
right
H let me see k
z
t z acts on down to give minus
down it acts on up to give up so it has
no effect on this term and it changes
the sign of this term I think I did it
right no yeah okay
minus now what about Sigma Z what does
it
do it flips the sign no it doesn't flip
it um gives Plus on this one and minus
on this
one so it changes the sign of this
one okay now we have to put it together
we have up
down up down with a minus sign so minus
one we have down up with down up minus
one cross terms give nothing up down
with down up gives nothing down up with
up down gives nothing there are two
terms you get a 2 over two
two- 2 over
2 equals
minus1 what does it say this is kind of
interesting um the expectation value of
Sigma X by itself was Zero the
expectation value of to X by itself was
Zero the expectation value of Sigma x *
tox is
-1 let's see if we can see why look at
the state here in this component over
here
obviously sorry this was Sigma Z Sigma Z
Sigma Z we were talking about Sigma Z
are opposite in both contributions here
Sigma Z time Sigma Z for this piece is
minus1 why is that this one's up this
one's down down if Sigma Z is Plus for
this one Sigma Z is minus for this one
the product is negative the product is
negative one for this one
also in fact if you think about it this
state is an igen Vector of Sigma Z times
to
Z what's the igen
value minus one so in fact this state is
a state in which if you measured the
product Sigma Z toi you would get minus
one every single
time so the expectation value is minus
one nevertheless the expectation value
of the
individual Sigma X sorry Sigma Z's and T
Z's is
zero all right so this is uh this is
beginning
to get some some of the flavor of what
an entangled state
is
the it simply doesn't behave
like you might expect two separate
systems which are just uh independent
and have always been
independent uh they behave let's try
this is this is undoubtedly going to get
boring now but let's do it anyway this
is plus minus we go back to the original
sandwich but instead of let's instead of
Sigma Z Let's
do let's do um Sigma X tox
all right so Sigma X time tox it's easy
to figure that out tox
flips the second entry Sigma X flips the
first entry all right so this object
here simply flips both entries without
changing any signs it flips no entry at
all uh it uh what I
say it um
yeah so what does it do it looks like
it
interchanges these two right
interchanges these two makes this one
minus and this one
plus now what's the inner
product up down with minus up down minus
one down up or minus down up with down
up minus one again again -2 over 2 =
-1 same exact thing
as and what would you guess about Sigma
y toy now there's nothing special about
the y- axis same thing also has an
expectation value equal to minus one so
all right this again this telling you
very clearly this can't be a product
state for a product State the
expectation value of a product like this
would just be the product of expectation
values and that's not what's going on
here so this is a highly entangled State
about as entangled as you can
get um we take the product of two
observables so that's two two operators
ESS so I think how I should think of
that physically is that one observation
Follow by another observation uh in this
case you in this casee remember
no you don't think of not in general no
in general it's just another operator if
it's her Mission it's another observable
it can be measured but in this case
since all sigmas commute with all TOS
you can think about measuring them both
simultaneously all right and in fact if
you measure them both simultaneously you
will simply discover the obvious fact
that they are oppositely
oriented all right let's do one more
let's do since I haven't worked it out
and I never worked it out I'm going to
work it out right now let's do to uh
Sigma x * to
Z let's do Sigma X oops what what did I
write here Sigma X to X all right let's
do Sigma
x times to Z and see what we get I don't
know the answer so let's do
it I have a suspicion of uh no I have a
suspicion okay we'll find
out what happens when t z acts on this
guy
here t z is just changes the sign
right t
z just if it's down you get minus one if
it's up you get plus
one say it again oh I flipped them
around yes you're right
good
yeah okay okay so to
[Music]
Z sees the down here and makes it minus
down it sees the up here and leaves it
alone okay now what does Sigma X do
Sigma X flips the first entry and so it
gives minus down
down minus now let's see it flips minus
up up right
and we have to take the inner
product with
this guy over here well nothing over
here matches anything over here so we
see that the answer in this case is zero
you see the answer is zero uh the
expectation value of Sigma
X time to Z or any non equal ones that's
equal to
zero
what does it say well I don't know the
main reason I did it is because I was
curious what the answer was but I also
did it just as an illustration of the
Machinery of calculating an expectation
value but these ones tell you clear
things what they tell you is that in a
very definite
sense the any given component of Sigma
and to the X component or the Y
component or the Z component are
oppositely
oriented
uh it's obvious here that for the Z
component they're oppositely oriented
huh this is opposite to this this is
opposite to this so in any of the
component State vectors here they're
oppositely oriented but we also found
something else out we found out that
they're oppositely oriented in the X
bases or in the Y bases any one of the
bases if you measure any one of the the
spins any component of the up spin
basically it automatically tells you
what the other one is what this is
telling you since it's telling you that
the product is always equal to minus one
in fact this is an igen Vector of the
product of any of these products it
tells you if you measure any component
for one of
them that you will get exactly the
opposite if you measure the upper one
the other one it's a
correlation it's a correlation a
statistical correlation that if you
measure one of the components of spin of
of Sigma then that and also the same
component for the other one they'll be
opposite because it doesn't tell you
much if you measure the X component of
this Spin and the Y component of that
spin that it doesn't tell you much but
it does tell you that if you measure the
same component of either of them they
will come out opposite
yeah
job so it appli I mean he dealing with a
system where these two spins are areed
in opposite direction and it seems like
it would be an up down kind of state is
that right or is
that no the kind of states that Bell
dealt with were entangled States up down
minus down up it's exactly what he's
dealt
with yeah will any interaction lead to a
state like this this yeah almost any
interaction between the spins will lead
to a state like
that
um yeah but did you say it's a
statistical correlation yes it's a
statistical correlation that um
statistical
look at this to some extent it's similar
to a trivial observation you know the
way I like to phrase it is I have a nick
I have a a penny and a dime in my pocket
all right I put my hand in my pocket I
take them out I don't look at them
without looking at them I give one to
Alice and one to Bob and then I tell
Alice and Bob to take off and uh you
know go uh go to the moon and go to
wherever you want to go then it's going
to be the case that if Alice looks at
her coin she instantly knows what Bob's
coin is right she sees if I got a dime
he's got a penny If he if I got a penny
he's got a dime uh that in
itself is not surprising there's nothing
uh in the past they were together some
correlation was established what was the
correlation the correlation was a
correlation that if Alice has a dime
then Bob has a penny and vice versa no
other possibilities were possible
so it was a correlation between uh
Alice's coin and Bob's coin and it was
an
anti-correlation if we called heads and
taals plus and one plus one and minus
one then if Alice's was plus one Bob is
minus one but the opposite is also
possible they don't know in
advance and yet when Alice is far away
and when Bob is far away Alice looks at
a coin and she instantly knows what Bob
is I assure you that does not violate
the special theory of
relativity and this kind with this kind
of correlation is
a this is called Einstein Rosen Podolski
correlation or entanglement um this is
the Quantum version of that same nickel
and dime story Penny and dime story real
nickels and real real properties yeah
yeah no there there is certainly a
difference there is certainly a
difference but just the idea
that by looking at something at one
place you instantly know something that
you didn't know a second ago about the
other place that's just statistical
correlation it's a tremendously common
thing in physics there's nothing special
about it the question is what is it
that's special and different about um
about this
entanglement and that's where John Bell
found something interesting he didn't
find nonlocality and we're going to talk
next time about what nonlocality means
in physics and what it was exactly that
John Bell
found um but I'm going to tell you right
now it was not
nonlocality it it looks like nonlocality
and the reason is because you're trying
to apply classical reasoning what what
John Bell said is you can't apply
classical reasoning to Quantum systems
that's what it came down to Quantum
systems are quantum mechanical and if
you try to apply classical reasoning
you're going to find
inconsistencies okay I can say it
another way I'll tell you another way
here's a way to say
it
um imagine you had a computer and you
try to simulate on that computer the
quantum mechanics of a single spin now
here's the way you would simulate it you
would be able to instruct the computer
to orient its um apparatus in an
arbitrary Direction in other words you
would put in coordinates for a
direction and when you put in the
coordinates for the direction the
computer would do some
calculation appeal to a random number
generator and spit out a plus one or a
minus
one there would be an algorithm that
would
say that if you do it over again
immediately that you'll spit out the
next same number number
again and that if you do it again you'll
spit out the same number again but you
might then say all right now let me make
it more interesting by adding in a a
mathematical magnetic field which allows
the spin to process what would you do
you would solve the sh the computer
would solve the schinger equation find
out what the state was after a little
bit of time calculate the probabilities
for up and down or whatever you decide
to measure calculate the probabilities
appeal to the random number generator
and spit out a number that was
statistically exactly what you should
get on the average from quantum
mechanics somebody who came to this
computer and started playing with it and
doing these experiments rotating his
apparatus in different
directions uh turning on magnetic fields
in other directions waiting varous
amounts of time and then telling the
computer measure this or that component
would reproduce exactly quantum
mechanics at least to the extent that
random number generators are possible
they're not exactly possible but you
know you can make pretty good random
numbers all right so that would be a
Quantum that wouldn't be a quantum
computer that would be a classical
computer
simulating Quantum
Behavior where somebody doing a little
experiment on it could be fooled into
think thinking that it was actually
dealing with a single electron inside
the computer and doing a Quantum
experiment it couldn't tell the
difference now the question is could you
do the same thing for two
spins in particular I want to do the
same thing for two spins and I want to
do it in such a way that one of the
spins all of its data is located in one
computer and all of the data for the
other spin is located in the other
computer now I can bring the computers
together have wires connecting them and
so forth for a while do arbitrary things
and then cut the wires and separate
them can I
simulate the quantum mechanics of the
two particle system in such a way that
it would appear that one of the
computers contained one particle and the
other computer contained the other
particle now remember this is a
classical computer two classical
computers and the answer is that the
only way you could do it would be to
have wires connecting the
computers at all times you could not do
it unless the
computers uh were capable of interacting
directly at a distance but that does not
mean that um that the system is
non-local non-local means that signals
can be propagated from one place to
another what it's telling you is you
simply can't
simulate quantum mechanics in a local
Way by a classical computer the logic of
quantum mechanics is different it simply
does not allow itself to be
faked by a computer unless that computer
is connected over large distances to
everything in the
world quantum mechanics manages to do
the same thing without having wires
connecting things however you can ask
the question does that constitute what
physicists call
nonlocality or what Einstein would have
called nonlocality it does not it does
not constitute in any way the ability to
send a message from one place to another
uh but we're going to come to that we'll
deal with
that uh no it it is fundamentally the
inability to simulate quantum mechanics
by classical computers unless the
classical computers are hooked up in a
highly non-local ways
for more please visit us at stanford.edu